Now let's take a look at a sample project scope and how it may look like.
الآن دعونا نلقي نظرة على عينة لنطاق مشروع وكيف يمكن أن يبدو.
Now it's important to keep in mind here that
الآن، من المهم أن نضع في اعتبارنا أن
project scopes vary significantly in their formats and depth.
نطاقات عمل المشاريع تختلف بشكل كبير في شكلها وحجمها.
The details required may vary depending on the client and the nature of work.
وقد تختلف التفاصيل المطلوبة حسب العميل وطبيعة العمل.
Now let's start by talking about some key elements in a project scope.
الآن دعونا نبدأ بالحديث عن بعض العناصر الرئيسية في نطاق المشروع.
We start off by defining the end goal of the project,
نبدأ بتحديد الهدف النهائي للمشروع،
which in this example is a WordPress website for a business consultancy firm.
وهو في هذا المثال موقع WordPress على شبكة الإنترنت لشركة استشارية تجارية.
Then a project scope may also include a deadline,
ويمكن أن يتضمن نطاق المشروع أيضًا موعد تسليم،
when the client wants the project to be done.
وهو موعد إنجاز المشروع وتسليمه للعميل.
A primary part of a project scope is the list of features or the work streams required.
وجزء أساسي من نطاق المشروع هو قائمة العناصر أو مسارات العمل المطلوبة.
In this case, the client has mentioned the sections they want in the website,
وفي هذه الحالة، ذكر العميل الأقسام التي يريدها في
a live chat,
محادثة حية مباشرة،
they also need an appointment scheduler and a module to send emails to users.
ويحتاج أيضًا إلى جدولة مواعيد ونموذج لإرسال رسائل إلكترونية إلى المستخدمين.
The client also wants an SSL security certificate,
ويحتاج أيضًا شهادة أمان (SSL)،
so the website can be accessed by using the HTTPS protocol.
حتى يمكن الوصول إلى الموقع باستخدام بروتوكول HTTPS.
You see these features will really give you an idea of the effort involved,
هذه المواصفات تعطيكم فكرة عن الجهد المطلوب في العمل
what questions you need to ask the clients,
ما هي الأسئلة التي تحتاج لطرحها على العميل؟
the sequence of what modules to build first and so on.
يجب أن تسأل عن ترتيب بناء النماذج وبأيهم تبدأ وهكذا.
Now, another important part of a project scope is
الآن، جزء هام آخر من نطاق المشروع هو
the detailed specification of each individual feature.
المواصفات التفصيلية لكل عنصر على حدة.
Just the name of the feature may not give
اسم الميزة فقط قد لا يعطي
a clear picture on what the client really wants to get done.
صورة واضحة لما يريد العميل فعله.
For example, here the project scope expands on the sections,
فعلى سبيل المثال هنا يتوسع نطاق المشروع ليشمل الأقسام،
saying that all the content will be provided by the client,
ويذكر أن العميل سيوفر المحتوى،
but the design and the images need to be worked on by the developer.
وعلى المطور أن يعمل على التصميم والصور.
In the appointment scheduler,
وفي جدولة المواعيد
the project scope specifies how the user will book
يحدد نطاق المشروع كيف يستطيع المستخدم حجز
an appointment and the kind of emails that need to be sent out.
موعد، ونوعية الرسائل الإلكترونية التي يجب إرسالها.
This tells the developer that an email module is needed,
هذا يوضح للمطور أن هناك حاجة إلى نموذج بريد إلكتروني،
which would increase the amount of effort involved.
مما سيزيد من الجهد المطلوب.
Now, these are some really basic elements that would indeed go and do a project score.
الآن، هذه هي بعض العناصر الأساسية التي من شأنها تحقيق نتائج المشروع.
As mentioned earlier, the format and depth of
وكما ذكرت سابقًا، فإن شكل وعمق
a project scope could vary from project to project and client to client.
الإطار والنطاق يختلف من مشروع لآخر ومن عميل لآخر.
For example, a project scope could include the cost and
فعلى سبيل المثال، يمكن أن يشمل نطاق المشروع التكاليف
the pricing structure of the project or
وهيكل التسعير أو
how periodically the status updates are scheduled.
مواعيد تحديث الحالة وجدولتها.
Larger projects have milestone delivery,
بالنسبة للمشاريع الكبيرة فقد يكون هناك مراحل ومحطات للتسليم،
which means interim versions of the output are delivered
مما يعني تسليم نسخ مرحلية من الناتج
at specific intervals instead of one delivery at the end.
على فترات محددة بدلًا من تسليم كامل في نهاية المشروع.
Those milestones could be included in the scope.
ويمكن إدراج محطات ومراحل التسليم في إطار المشروع.
In a large organization,
في المؤسسات الكبيرة
even the names of the team members are included in the scope.
يجب أن يتضمن إطار المشروع أسماء أعضاء فريق العمل.
These team members are those whom the freelancer needs
وهم الأشخاص الذين يحتاج الموظف الحر
to interact with depending on their job function.
للتفاعل معهم طبقًا لوظيفتهم.
Sometimes, external or internal dependencies
وفي بعض الأحيان يمكن إدراج اعتمادات خارجية أو داخلية
may be included that could affect the project.
من شأنها التأثير على المشروع.
For example, module set need to be provided by another business unit,
فعلى سبيل المثال، قد يلزم توفير نموذج عمل من طرف قطاع عمل آخر،
which are a prerequisite for us to make progress on our module.
وقد يكون ذلك أمر يتوقف عليه عملنا في إتمام النموذج.
That said, the intent of the project scope,
ولهذا فإن الغرض من تحديد نطاق المشروع
as we discussed earlier, is mainly twofold.
كما ناقشناه من قبل يتمثل في أمرين رئيسيين.
The end goal of the project and
الهدف النهائي للمشروع،
the building blocks that are required by the client to reach the end goal.
و الخطوات التي يحتاجها العميل لبلوغ الهدف النهائي.